this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at sc-radio.net
SE radio is brought to you by the IEEE
computer Society software Magazine
online at computer.org software
[Music]
are you a software engineer developer
consultant architect manager no matter
what your role is we want to hear from
you please take a minute to complete our
listener survey to help us make SC radio
even more relevant to you
just go to se Dash radio.net
survey2023 to share with us that's
se-radio.net survey2023
thanks for your support of the show hi
this is Jeremy Jung for software
engineering radio today I'm talking to
Dr Leo Porter he's an associate teaching
professor of computer science at the
University of California San Diego and
he co-founded the Computing education
research laboratory there I'm also
joined by Dr Daniel zingaro who is an
associate teaching professor of computer
science at the University of Toronto and
he's also the author of the book learn
to code by solving problems and the book
algorithmic thinking they are co-authors
of the book learn AI assisted Python
Programming Leo and Dan welcome to
software engineering radio thank you for
having us Jeremy I really appreciate
your podcast thanks Jeremy the first
thing we could start with is why this
book and why now how did you decide on
like okay this is the thing we need to
do now so Dan really early when llms
first kind of were coming out of me and
seen on the scene for programming he
started playing with them for program
projects and I think Dan really quickly
realized that they'd have a big impact
on how we teach programming so he
reached out to me and said I really need
to give him a try and after I play with
him for a while I had the exact same
realization that this is going to change
how we teach programming in a
pre-dramatic way
so having realized that having realized
we had to change our introductory cs1
courses we knew we need to do that
but in order to teach that class we have
to have a book that we could assign our
students so that would go along with the
class and so we knew we had to change
the class but we also knew we had to
have a book for it and given the the
timeline to write books we started in
the book first and so that's how it got
started I guess we figured out that our
course had to change first before we
knew exactly how it had to change one
thing we learned early on was that the
kinds of assignments we give in our
introductory courses they're just solved
by these tools like chat GPT and GitHub
copilot so we knew something had to
change and then it's just a matter of
figuring out what and so we spent quite
a bit of time with these tools and we
started to realize that what's going to
change is the skills that our students
need to learn to be effective using
these tools so like before these tools
we would spend a lot of time teaching
syntax and students struggle quite a bit
with learning syntax which I mean it's
very frustrating right because you can't
even do anything until you get the
syntax right and you're getting all
these errors like missing colons and you
know mismatched braces and stuff like
that uh so it's actually good that the
llms are doing the Syntax for the
students but you know just because that
skills not needed as much doesn't mean
that there aren't still skills for
students to learn so instead of syntax
other things become more important so
for example Leo and I realized that
reading code is going to be extremely
important even more so than before I
think if that's even possible and that's
because sometimes you're going to get
back code that just doesn't work and so
we realize that students are going to
need to be able to read the response
that they get to see if the code looks
reasonable or not right and then if the
code is unreasonable then they need to
read more code and look at other
Solutions right that they get from the
llm other things they can do as well
like messing around with the prompt and
so on but they're going to need to be
able to read code throughout the process
so we just kind of kept on using these
tools and documenting the skills that
students are going to need and we're
just going to realize that all the
skills students are going to need are
skills we would want to teach anyway so
like one more example is testing right
so students may now not have an
understanding of every last detail of
the Python language like they would
before and so then that makes testing
even more important right than it was
they need to verify that the code
they're getting is correct and so they
have to be very good at writing test
cases and and you know similar for
debugging we need our students to have
strong debugging skills again even
potentially stronger than before right
because if the code isn't working they
need to First determine what the code is
doing to be able to fix it and then I
guess one more I'll mention is problem
decomposition and this is a big one I
think this is going to come up a couple
times probably in our talk today but
llms struggle when you give them tasks
that are too large and students need to
know how to break problems down into
small components so that the llm can
solve each one and you know have a good
chance of getting it right
kind of piggyback off of that you may be
hearing these skills and saying oh these
are absolute essential skills every
software engineer should know these are
being taught right now right and the
answer is not really like these aren't
core topics in a lot of introductory CS
classes because so much time is spent on
syntax and so fairly early on when we
kind of realize these skills would be so
essential we got really excited because
these are skills we want to teach in our
classes and the llms are now giving us
the ability to do that I think that's
interesting about the syntax comment
because you were saying how reading is
going to be more important than ever
because you have llm generating the code
and you need to understand that code
that's being generated and understand
that it does what you think it does and
so I wonder if when you say you spend
less time on syntax is it because you
feel like they're going to generate this
code and they're sort of organically
going to pick up syntax that way versus
having to focus on it at the start I'm
just trying to picture what you see
changing there yeah Jeremy so I was I
was speaking specifically about syntax
errors which don't generally happen when
you're using llms and I also agree with
you you need to know what the code is
doing but you can do that without
worrying about each specific piece of
syntax like you're going to need to know
what the keywords do for sure but
missing you know brackets and colons and
oh there needs to be like a blank line
here indentation a lot of this kind of
thing
is done for the most part correctly
by the llms so yeah I agree with you you
need to be able to identify the
structures right so in our book actually
Leo and I have a couple of chapters on
reading code and I don't think we ever
break down a line of code into its
individual tokens
we do talk about the main structures
like ifs and loops and functions and all
that but compared to other books I think
or other ways of teaching where you
would focus on the micro level we try to
focus on the line level now because we
want our students to be able to grasp
what each line is doing I guess more
than each token yeah maybe to add to
that a bit it's almost if you think
about the Advent of block-based
languages it was to make sure that the
essentially the author can't make syntax
mistakes right is the whole purpose of
kind of block based languages and
they're huge for introductory
programming especially in like K-12 and
it sends LMS do is because they never
give you back Ron syntax so they almost
almost never give you back Ryan syntax
and so it takes away that kind of
cognitive burden of making sure you
handle the token level as Amazon I'm
curious so you said the syntax is
correct but what are the typical
mistakes you see coming back from these
llms is it a logical mistake or is it
ever something that that actually
doesn't compile I'm kind of curious what
your experience has been I think the
more common errors that we've been
seeing are logical so it misinterprets
the prompt that you're giving it it
essentially tries to solve a problem
that's different than what you're trying
to solve it may have bugs in it so it is
in fact trying to solve the right
problem but it it's off by one is maybe
replicating some mistake that it found
in the large code base and so most
mistakes are going to be you need to
write test cases run it that mistake is
then going to show up when the test
cases catch it and then you'll have to
try to fix it if the students can read
the code if we train them well to read
the code often you'll look at the
response and the response is just not
even trying to solve the right problem
you can usually pick that up pretty
quick I think the students will be
learned to do that and then they can
just say okay this is clearly not the
right answer and use the different tools
and say vs code to find another answer
and then pick one that's right or change
their prompt to get a rest response
that's right go through that whole flow
but then some point another it will give
an answer that looks right and then I
think all of us as software Engineers
know that even the code looks right it
may not be and so then they have to
actually write the test cases get some
level of confidence that's actually
working right before they'll know and so
sometimes sometimes you know really
quick it's just clearly wrong it's
solving the wrong problem and sometimes
it looks right but it actually has some
bugs that need to be fixed I guess one
thing that struck me is how much a
change in the prompt can matter uh Leo
you know we've seen this over and over
again where we'll write a prompt it
seems fine to us and then we'll realize
oh there are actually two different ways
of interpreting this and the ambiguity
of English strikes again right and so
it's just amazing to me how clarifying
the prompts how many times that fixes
the code not always we definitely have
examples where that's not the case but
more often than not in my experience
changing the prompt appropriately has a
bigger than anticipated effect on the on
the code it's amazing everything about
the prompt in terms of like Doc strings
for functions adding the test cases
certainly help sometimes it is
surprising sometimes that you can add
the test cases to the prompt and it'll
still give you back code that does not
actually pass that test case because it
vs code and co-pilot doesn't actually
run the code that comes back from the
llm but I do find the test cases dues
tend to help with the quality response
you get back as a part of your prompt
you're asking it to implement some
functionality and you're also asking it
to write these tests for that same
functionality
oh no sorry it's more the doc test kind
of format so you're writing let's say
you're in your function signature and
then you have the description of the
function in a doc string and then
towards the end of Doc string I'm
articulating the test cases that I
intend to use and the articulate the
test cases that I intend to use helps it
come with a better prompt I haven't
found it to be great at writing test
cases I haven't spent a ton of time with
this by the time that I have spent it
tends to want to do almost like a brute
for search of all possible inputs as
opposed to doing okay well here's a
couple common here the edge cases now I
can feel fairly good about it it doesn't
seem to have that intuition yet
for the most part we're writing the test
cases ourselves and we're going to be
teaching the students how to write the
test cases themselves as well yeah so
Leo and I have actually made a conscious
decision to have students write test
cases from scratch even though you could
play around with the llm and have it you
know try to generate test cases whether
it's flawed or not we still want
students to do this from scratch we
think that writing test cases is a skill
we want our students to have sometimes
what these models will generate like you
were saying has logical errors and
hopefully if you're writing the test
cases you've put some thought into them
and your test cases are actually
checking the correct Behavior so then
you have the llm generate the
implementation it's running against
tests where you know what the correct
answer should be and so it generates
something that's incorrect you've kind
of caught it you're not totally relying
on it telling you everything is is good
you know it's confidence in something
that's like you personally can't see
it's just what the machine gave you
maybe it takes away one layer of
uncertainty too Jeremy right like so the
code could be wrong right and then if it
generates test cases okay the test cases
could be wrong too and maybe you get
unlucky and two wrongs make a right and
then your test cases pass for the wrong
reason so yeah we really want to hone
this skill in our students and and it
like Leo said earlier These intro
courses used to be so full of low-level
syntax concerns that we we didn't do
testing properly you know we all try to
cover testing but I think we're going to
be able to cover it a lot more detailed
now I think we're enthusiastic about how
students will approach testing when
you're working with the LM is fairly
anecdotal but when they interact with us
talking about testing often students
aren't testing their code because they
wrote it and so of course it's right
right it's like this really famous kind
of bug in human thinking right is that
if you're right of course the computer
is going to interpret what you're saying
right and so students tend to trust
their code in a way that professional
software Engineers never would and I
think because it's coming from this
third party that you know is wrong it's
coming from the llm that can often make
mistakes I think they're going to be
more inclined to actually engage in
those testing practices kind of knowing
about the fallibility of the llm you're
Shifting the order I mean there is test
driven development that some people
practice but I feel like probably what's
most common is you write the
implementation yourself and then then
you'll go and see like oh did this thing
I I wrote did it do what I thought it
should do whereas this is kind of
flipping it where it's the large
language model is going to write my code
so I'm just going to start with the test
and then I'll ask it to write me the
code code and maybe that will kind of
make test driven development be the
default I think that students may want
to engage more in kind of test driven
development because I want to think more
about what exactly should this function
be doing how should it behave what kind
of inputs and outputs should expect and
then it can kind of write the prompt to
co-pilot or whatever llm is using to
express those inputs and outputs well
they're more apt to get a good answer
from the LM and they've kind of already
got their test cases worked out as well
so they can immediately just go right
into the testing stage and see if the
prompt came back right and you mentioned
writing a prompt to implement a specific
function have you found that they work
well at the function level but if you
try to ask it to build something more
broad that that's kind of when it has
problems so I think in general llms do
work best at the function level we have
tried to get it to generate bigger apps
Collections and functions and it can
work but sometimes it does do worse but
also we want students to do the problem
decomposition for themselves and break
up the problem into individual functions
even though maybe the llm could work
with bigger chunks of code we want
students to do it and one reason is so
that they can customize what they get
from the LOM so in the book we have a
bunch of examples where you could
probably just throw it at the LOM and
get an answer and you know eventually
get it to work but I think at that point
making changes to it might be trickier
than it would be if you knew the
architecture of what you were building
so in the book we have a bunch of top
down design diagrams and we want
students to understand what they're
building at that level like at the
function level instead of like we said
earlier instead of like at the token
level or the line level and so like in
this example you're thinking more from a
learning perspective you want the
student to look at the big picture
figure out okay what are all the
different functions or parts of my
application break that down and then
feed those individually to these large
language models I'm wondering from like
let's say you're a professional software
engineer and your interest is more and I
want to make the thing and less so and I
want to learn how to make the thing in
that case do you feel like you could
feel confident in giving the large
language model a larger piece of the
design or do you still feel like it's
good to have of that overall structure
done by the developer and then just be
very targeted about how you use the
large language model I think that's a
tricky question is we haven't worked
with these tools heavily in a
professional programming setting I think
often when we're thinking about large
design of software you're going to be
working on teams talking with other
members of the team about the interfaces
and things like that and so I'd be
pretty hesitant to Outsource that that
thinking to the the llm because the
communication between the team still has
to happen even if it weren't for that I
can't think of it as a probabilities so
essentially whenever you ask copilot or
any of these LMS to do a task the more
it has to write to get the kind of more
likely it's going to make a mistake and
so that's kind of why I like the
function level it seems like partially
because it's not that much code that
tends to write so you help to avoid kind
of the probabilistic problem but also
because it's learned on a huge code base
that has lots and lots of functions that
have been implemented it tends to do
well at that that's solving the function
kind of task I think the way you put it
as Outsourcing that design or that
decision is interesting because yeah if
you are working on a team and whether
it's in code review or just in a
discussion often people will ask well
why did you do it this way or why is
this the you know good way to design it
and if you kind of handed that off to an
llm maybe your answer is I don't know
it's just what it it told me which
foreign
Ty told me actually yeah that doesn't
seem a good answer we've kind of been
talking in more a general sense of
working with llms and you've mentioned
how you're going to be teaching
introductory computer science courses
this coming quarter semester and so when
you teach these classes what tools are
you going to recommend your students use
and yeah maybe you could go into that a
bit absolutely so we're going to be
recommending at least for my class I'm
going to be recommending that they use a
vs code with copilot I just like the
integration of the IDE with the
interactions with the llm I think it
avoids just a whole bunch of copy
pasting from another interface into your
IDE to then run it I think it also
reduces the barrier of them kind of
immediately getting the code and then
testing it right there in the
environment I'm sure any of the other
tools of work it just that seems to have
worked well for us when we write in the
book and that's that's actually the
technique we recommend in the book as
well so that would be the primary tool
for the students writing the code in
addition to having them using copilot
with in the IDE for a lot of the code
generation depending on where things are
at with copilot X which is right now
available through waitlist that's
available publicly I think we're going
to be recommending that because it has a
co-pilot chat feature which can be
really nice to interact with and the
main use that that we're going to be
encouraging students to use whether it
be copilot chat or a chat gbt is in just
a conversation with the llm about
particularly modules and libraries so if
you are diving into merging PDFs which
Dan did a great job in one of the
chapters in our book talking about if
you want to dive into that well what
library should be using in Python for
that and we found that the llms do a
really good job of this of actually
saying here are the different libraries
you could use hear the pros and cons of
them these are the ones that need to be
actually have an additional install done
or these ones are coming with vanilla
python they're actually really good at
kind of giving you what you should use
for the various libraries and so that's
one other way that we we're going to be
encouraging the students to use the LMS
yeah so whenever the students or the
junior programmer doesn't know how or
doesn't think they can do something in
base python we have them interact with
the chat and ask so another example that
comes to mind from the book is we have a
chapter writing some games and so for
most games including the two that we've
got in the book you need to be able to
Generate random numbers right so how do
you do that and so in the past you would
have used a search engine stack Overflow
or something and you would have found
some sample code and you would have
pasted it in to your file and made
variable name changes and things like
that and so what we do now is we ask
chat okay I need to generate some random
numbers how do I do it and then it will
come back to you with a few options and
then you can systematically work through
those options if you like and you can
ask okay is this one built into python
or not and then it will tell you oh this
one's not and you say oh okay so like
how do I install this and then no does
it work on all os's or just Windows
right so we guide The Reader through
these questions that you could have to
help you make a decision and I think
what I like the most about this is not
having to learn apis like yet another
API like I don't I don't think I have
room you know in my like brain for any
more apis and and what's cool is I've
forgotten like every API that we've used
in the book so we have like examples of
emerging PDFs and removing duplicate
images from directories from like
people's phones and stuff like that and
I don't know I don't know which Library
it's using and I'm totally okay with
that right like I just I wanted to get
the job done I wanted to write a tool
and the tool got written and it used
some sort of library and it worked great
and I didn't have to look through the
documentation for that library and
figure out like which functions do I
have to call and things like that so I
know it can be fun you know it could be
fun to really learn an API well but a
lot of people
they don't want to program for
programming's sake like they just want
to get work done right so you know while
I fully admit to enjoying programming
just for the sake of programming I do a
lot of competitive programming problems
just for fun you know it's like Sunday
morning and it's like hey you know I got
like a and I got an hour to work on
something let me work on this little
competitive programming problem a lot of
people they're not motivated by that
they're motivated by consequences of
code and this is one thing about llms
that I'm very excited about is
you can just make a lot more progress
without having to learn
what these people may believe is just
useless knowledge right like does it
really matter how I should invoke this
API right to merge PDF files I mean the
answer from many people is no like they
just want the result to happen and I
love how we can kind of match what they
deem important right with the llms it's
like a new level of abstraction for for
many people there's a couple of
audiences that come to our introductory
classes and what Dan's talking about
here is one of the things I'm most
excited about with this and that's the
students who come and take just one
programming class I know this is
probably a different audience than a lot
of people listening right now but the
people who just take one programming
class is required for further major they
I just wanted to explore it a little bit
but they don't go into this as a as a
career I think a lot of those students
right now if you ask a year later to
program something do any of these tasks
that we're talking about right now I
doubt they're able to even if they did
really well in that class and that's
really disappointing right if they
they've taken a programming class they
should be able to to do something with
that be a year or even five years later
and I really believe that if you teach
them the skills of interacting with
these llms they'll be able to do these
tasks later they'll be able to come back
and go you know I don't remember any of
the Python syntax I don't remember even
how to get started with this but you
know what I'm just going to ask uh
co-pilot how do I go about merging these
PDFs evidence directory and then the
copal chat comes back and says oh you
might use this and that and then they go
oh I remember I remember how to write
these functions and I just said you have
to give a prompt I think they could
really do it that's a bit of a game
changer right that means a larger
portion of our society will be able to
write code and use in a useful way I'm
just really excited about that I think
it's gonna be really nice after the
changes happen I can totally see in the
context of someone who's not seeing it
as a career or someone who is like
hasn't done it in a while these tools
can be incredibly useful right or it can
even get you interested in this field at
all right like a lot of people they they
struggle through the syntax and then
they decide like oh this is not for me
even though like they had something
really cool they wanted to build and
maybe these kind of tools can get them
over that home exactly I think there's a
population of students and it varies a
bit by demographics who come to computer
science with really the best motives in
mind right they want to make their goals
in their life or to make the world a
better place and they want to achieve
those goals and if you spend the first
three quarters or three semesters
working with them and all they're seeing
is syntax they're not actually solving
anything meaningful it starts to create
this disconnect of what their goals are
for their life and what they think the
goals of our career are of course as a
computer science I want to say stick it
out you know if you go into the fourth
fifth class you'll see seen how these
are really useful tools that can make
Society a better place but it'd be
really nice to front load that and have
them solving useful problems much
earlier and seeing that computer science
can be used in really nice ways and So
within the context of people who are
studying computer science will
eventually who may become professional
software developers things like that
something more long-term where it
becomes more of a craft the code that
comes back from these large language
models sometimes it could be something
that's like not maybe the most easy to
read or it may be doing something
inefficiently and I'm wondering from
your perspective how users of these
tools should think about that and
recognize when that's a problem in the
first couple of courses typically in the
Cs program we don't spend much time on
efficiency the reason is that there's
just so much to learn early on and we
worry about overwhelming people with the
too much for them to process it at once
and we don't want to prevent students
from becoming interested by
giving them all of these requirements
early on so typically we you know we
push efficiency down the road into like
a data structures course for example but
your question points to another reason
why we've decided to teach some of the
skills we teach early on so if a student
you know came up to Leo or me and said
hey you know like I want to generate a
phishing code how do I do it my answer
would be so like get familiar with
programming first but you are learning
the skills necessary where you'll be
able to look at code later because you
know how to read it still right it's not
something that you don't understand
you're going to know it we're going to
spend lots of time on code reading and
so later I think we can just teach
efficiency the way we always did so you
know doing time complexity analysis on
on the code and they're still going to
understand what the code is doing so I
don't think this is going to change much
in in the earliest courses so the point
about code readability I might add that
certainly they're going to get back some
some code that's maybe not the best
style and may not be as readable but
what's kind of interesting is that
students aren't exposed to a lot of
different styles kind of in our existing
courses right they they see the code
that they write and they see the code
that the professor writes and gives them
and there's not much else and so I mean
we're going to need data and we're gonna
need research to know this for sure but
I suspect them seeing lots of different
code Styles and having to read those
different code Styles may actually
inform them better than we do now about
what makes code more readable and then
they might be able to employ that as I
go forward and when you sing they're
gonna read different styles and things
like that are you referring to code
they're going to see from the llm or are
you talking about them reading just
other code bases in their classes or
their professional work oh I'm sorry
yeah I was referring to the code they'll
see from the LL come back in all these
different ways they'll have different
styles and it'll have different
approaches to solving it right sometimes
it'll come back with like this one line
Lambda expression thing that solves it
and they'll have no idea how that works
and they'll they'll ask for a different
answer and they'll get a much more
user-friendly first programming
experience kind of code back and they'll
be able to understand that and go okay
this is the kind of code that I want to
see not this this other thing that was
completely not readable Yeah by default
you can get it to give you 10 code
segments to solve the problem right so
if you kind of cool if we ask students
about each of them or each of the 10
which ones are right which ones have
bugs which ones have good style which
ones have bad style it's like a built-in
learning opportunity right there so oh
that's true yeah and so the 10 things
that Dave's referring to is if you do
control enter and vs code when you're
working with a copilot it'll give you
back 10 possible responses and your toy
right Dan you could just say of these 10
how readable are they are they right and
there's lots of fun things you can do to
ask students questions and often many of
them are right with just subtly
different ways of solving the problem I
mean I'll admit to having some fun
looking through all of the suggestions
just to kind of see what the variability
is and when there's a lot of variability
I really like it because like Leo said
it exposes people to different styles
they may not have seen before and it may
encourage you to ask questions right
like why does this one work right I've
tested it it doesn't look like it should
work why does it work I feel like that's
the beginning of a pretty powerful
learning experience right there yeah
that makes sense to me because I think
about how
when a lot of people are doing software
development before all these llms they
will search on the internet and go okay
what's an existing answer for this thing
I'm trying to do they'll find a post on
stack Overflow and they'll find the
accepted answer and it'll be like okay
this is it this is the solution whereas
at least in this case it seems like you
can go like okay well here's 10
potential Solutions and at least you get
a little bit more exposure to what are
the different ways you could do it
exactly and it's nice for them to see
these different options and I think
there is for professional software
Engineers seeing that stack Overflow
post so like here's the accepted answer
integrating that into your code isn't a
big jump for a lot of us but I do want
to stress that for the intro students it
often is a really big jump just the oh
how do I change around this I would this
was the interface for this function but
I'm asked to have this other interface
with a function and they really can
struggle in that domain and so I think
copilot These llms are nice and that
they give back answers that are more
tailored to the existing code that
they're working with and will reduce
that barrier them trying to incorporate
the answer
so it seems kind of overall when you're
talking about people who are using
programming in a more professional
capacity
the code style and efficiency that will
probably be taught very similarly to
however it is now where you basically
have to get exposed to different styles
and types of code get exposed to the
algorithms and and that will allow you
to read the answers you get back better
so the answers you get back from the llm
with the knowledge you gained from these
later courses you'll be able to tell
like okay this level of complexity or
this has like exponential performance
implications that kind of thing
so I think the performance piece is
really important I mean I appreciate you
bringing it up I think I'm kind of
curious what percentage of the time
professional programmers are really
spending optimizing the code that they
write I suspect a lot of the code that's
written is pretty straightforward you
already know how to work with a database
you're working with you already know how
to write the queries for that you're
just you're still doing something that
that certainly thought provoking but
it's not the hard work of oh how am I
going to write design the right
algorithm for this to get the exact best
run time and so I think there are some
times that that does matter but those
may be the times that the LMS aren't as
helpful and they're still going to be a
pretty big need for programmers who know
how to do that themselves
yeah I mean I I think that of course
this is going to vary from industry to
industry but Dan you're talking about
learning apis and I feel like a lot of
jobs are learning apis and gluing them
together yeah I would agree but I wonder
what can happen if some of that's
automated right so maybe people who are
gluing apis together will be able to get
even more done right incorporate even
more apis in the same amount of time
that they've been doing it now I don't
know if that job changes as dramatically
as it seems I guess there's this tension
between people having to change jobs or
become more efficient in the current job
and you know obviously I hope it's the
latter and there is some recent evidence
that it could end up being the latter
just more productive people overall
building you know bigger software
incorporating more apis than before and
now overloading yourself so we'll see
you know how it all turns out but I'm
hopeful that we'll just be doing our
jobs better in that context sometimes
people will say that the reading of code
and comprehending code can sometimes be
more difficult than writing the code and
in fact can sometimes take you more time
like let's say you've built out a
project and now you need to add new
features well to add the feature you
have to understand the code base that
existed before
and so when we talk about llms in the
context of not programming but just
general writing people talk about the
fact that it's easy to generate more
writing right we can generate more
documents blog posts more articles that
sort of thing and with code it sounds
like it will be similar right where
it'll be easier for us to write more
code generate more code but I wonder if
either of you think it's a concern that
we'll be generating so much code that
now we'll have so much we won't be able
to even have the time to understand all
of it I haven't thought much about the
Centurion so much code that you can't
understand I mean I think if we're
generating code I'm really hoping
someone's testing it making sure it
works right and stuff and so I guess it
depends what level of the interface are
we looking at but I have thought a fair
bit about what you described early on in
your question which was diving to a big
code base figuring out what needs to be
changed and changing it that is a really
common task especially for like new
software engineers and their their first
jobs right and it is also the one that's
really well documented in the education
literature CS education literature that
we aren't teaching them to do like we
almost always are giving them write
these functions are really well defined
or write the code all from yourself but
we rarely ever give them large code
bases to learn from now I don't think
diving into a large code base and trying
to understand how it works is the right
thing for like an intro class and we're
mainly talking about students first
learning to program here but I am
encouraged that we are teaching Karine
as kind of a first level skill when I
think current programming courses teach
code reading write in parallel with
writing so a lot of the writings
happening very early before they even
know how to read well and so I think
there's some optimism here that if we
teach code reading first and make it a
core skill
they'll be better set up in the later
classes to maybe take on those large
projects where they tackle the exact
problem you're describing which is also
the exact thing they're gonna have to do
when they get to do their jobs
yeah it also kind of I wonder sometimes
when you're writing code you'll write it
in a certain way because it's tedious to
write a lot of code right like you'll
make something generic in such a way
where you can reuse it
and maybe reduce the amount of lines of
code but then when you
have something generate that code
maybe it'll be a solution that is a lot
more code than you would have written
personally and it works but by Nature
the fact that it was easy to generate
you chose that solution versus one that
maybe was more generic and had less code
and I'm not sure if that makes sense but
I'm kind of curious if the use of these
models will sort of change maybe how we
write code I'm kind of wondering if the
amount of code we throw away is going to
increase
exponentially because if you spend time
working on something you're probably
going to keep it but I wonder because
Jeremy like what you said it's so easy
to generate code now so I've had this
thought
where I'm not sure how much I believe
myself here but should we be storing The
Prompt like not the dot py file right
like just Store The Prompt and then if
you do have to regenerate the code later
maybe you got to make some tweaks or
something you just change the prompt and
then rerun it because code is you know
it's not there yet but it's coming free
right it's becoming you can generate as
much of it as you want and so I wonder
how much of it and so there's a lot of
code already that you write once and you
run it once and then you get rid of it
or lose it or whatever and I wonder if
that practice will increase so it's like
okay you know I want to do this data
analysis
okay so you write a prompt you get some
code you generate some graph and then
you just don't even think about it you
just get rid of it and then maybe later
you want another similar analysis and
you just do it again right so I kind of
Wonder because there's maybe less
ownership now of code right you didn't
like sweat as much to write the code so
maybe more of it gets thrown away and
completely say see what you're saying
Dan so you have the prompt and you add
it won't perform some form of data
analysis and you want to tweak it to a
slightly different data analysis I
wouldn't go into the I mean right now if
I wrote the code from scratch I would go
into the code and find that one spot
that I need to change and I would tweak
it but if I'm just generating the code I
would just tweak The Prompt and then get
a new piece of code that does exactly
what I want there without having to
fight with a code to find the one spot
to change yeah you know how how it can
take a long time to re-familiarize
yourself with a program that you wrote
six months ago you know it's like oh
yeah it's variable temp one like what's
this four again right you know maybe I
think we've all been there yeah right
but yeah I don't know it's just a
thought I've been having it's like so
now when I hear people talking about
code maintenance for example like using
you know good variable names and
consistent style and stuff in my head
I'm thinking well you know is the code
the artifact now is it still the
artifact and right now you know of
course it is but you know fast forward a
little while maybe some of what I just
said sort of becomes true about just
getting to perhaps kind of a larger
issue about what is the interface that
we work with as programmers I've been
thinking about this a lot just because I
teach my backgrounds I have a PhD in
computer architecture and so I teach the
classes that do machine code and
assembly code and their core classes for
computer scientists because you need to
know how computers work and I think
that's a core component understanding
that but we don't start by teaching the
students machine code like no one wants
to learn how to program a machine at
least I can't imagine anyone wanting to
learn that and we've kind of cognitively
picked python or Java right now the most
common two programming language to learn
from because they're easy to learn
they're easy to read the code tends to
be more understandable when you read it
it tends to be a little bit more
forgiving when you write it and so we
pick these because we think they're nice
interfaces they're convenient for
programmers and they're convenient for
new Learners and it just seems to make
sense that the llm may be that next step
of interface that we start choosing the
the catch is because it can be wrong
it's not like a compiler a compiler is
deterministic it's going to be shy of
that maybe one time in your career you
find a compiler bug like the compiler is
always right this time the llm isn't
always right and so I'm not sure how
this is all going to play out you can
imagine the elements in the new
interface and all we ever store is is
code problems and we don't ever even see
the code perhaps one scenario and the
other is we do in fact still interact
with the LMS and still after the code
but I think it's too early to kind of
know where this is all going to fall but
we could see some big shifts I think in
the field over the next few years yeah I
think that's pretty interesting to think
about what Dan had mentioned where yeah
you could check in your prompt and maybe
a set of test cases
for the app that's supposed to come out
and yeah maybe that's your alternative
to the actual source code especially for
things that like you were saying are
used not that frequently or maybe you
only use it once
and so the quality of the actual code is
maybe less so important in terms of
readability and things like that and as
long as you can reliably reproduce that
thing yeah maybe that does make sense
the reliable reproduction could be the
tricky part and maybe even something
that you you start doing where you tag
it don't try to reproduce this like we
actually spend a whole bunch of time on
this it's super optimized like don't
think the LM is going to give you this
answer again so I'll keep the code along
with the prompt keep the code too don't
scratch that because the LM is not going
to do better and in some cases you're
like yeah the alarm's gonna do a pretty
good job on this and so feel free to
just regenerate it maybe we have to
distinguish between code that you can
just get out of an llm no problem and
code that people have spent time working
on yeah I like that yeah
humans were here
exactly yeah this is the 30th iteration
of this code we generated and we
verified that this one's good so just
just
it's a interesting future we we might be
heading into
so one thing you mentioned a little bit
earlier is the the tools that you're
going to recommend to your students it
sounds like it's primarily going to be
GitHub co-pilot and GitHub copilot X for
the chat interface and one thing about
these tools is these are tools by
commercial companies right these are
tools by openai and Microsoft they're
tools that you have to pay a
subscription fee to use you have to send
your code to a commercial server and I
wonder if that aspect concerns you at
all the fact that the foundations that
our students are learning on is kind of
reliant on these companies and these
cloud services
I think it's an amazing question I think
to some degree
these are the tools that professional
software Engineers are using and so
there's a bit of an obligation as
instructors to teach them the tools that
they're going to be using as
professionals going forward
I think right now they're free to use
for education's sake and so as long as
that stays the case I'm a little more
comfortable with it if it started to
move to a pay model for education I
think there could be some really big
problems with equity
and it's not just true for computer
science but I'll start with computer
science I mean if it's computer science
and we start making it where you would
have to pay to get access to these
models or use these models then whether
we tell the students they can use it or
not they still can use them and so
there's going to be some students the
wealthier students who may have access
to these who have been able to learn
better from that I used to be able to
solve better homeworks with these that's
super scary and you can imagine the same
thing for even just K-12 education right
if you're thinking about them writing
essays for homeworks or anything else if
it's a pay model then the students who
have the money will pay for it and get
access these tools and the students who
don't won't you could imagine all these
kind of socioeconomic divides that
already exist only being exacerbated by
these tools if they switch to this pay
model so that has me very worried
There's real ethical issues we have to
think about when we're using them the
other ethical I kind of want to mention
is just the copyright and the notion of
ownership and I think it's important for
us as instructors to engage age students
in the conversation about what it means
to create content and intellectual
property and how these models are built
and what they're building off of and
just engage in that ethical conversation
with the students I don't think we as a
society have figured this out I think
there's gonna be some time both legally
and ethically before we have the right
answers but at the very least you need
to talk to the students about these
challenges so they know what's going on
and they can engage in the debate yeah
just to underscore that Leo this is the
reason we're doing research on the first
version of the course that Leo's
teaching we need research on the impacts
of llms on students
especially we need to know if students
benefit from this in what ways they
benefit how are these benefits
distributed across demographic groups we
have a long and sad history in computer
science of inequities in who takes our
courses who succeeds in our courses
we're very aware of this and it's
unacceptable to make that situation
worse than it already is so we're going
to be carefully doing our research on
this first offering of the course
so we've mostly been talking about the
benefits of using these tools in classes
and in education we just mentioned the
possible inequities if you don't have
access to those things I wonder if from
either of you if there are negatives you
see to this technology whether that's
the impact on what people learn or in
anything else like are there downsides
you see to the use of this technology
yeah so in addition to the important
inequity concerns that we just talked
about I have a concern about students
using the tools in ways that don't help
them learn the skills we think they need
so it's a power tool and you can get
pretty far I think without being
systematic and how you work with it and
without testing without debugging you
know it's kind of magic right now and so
I can imagine a lot of students just
taking off at you know 100 miles an hour
and yeah so one of the things we have to
worry about in these initial courses is
convincing students that there really
are principles to using this technology
you can't just type something and get an
answer and then go party and so that is
one of my concerns that's one of the
negatives it's super powerful so before
you can't just type some Python and make
it work but now you can sort of type in
whatever you want and kind of get
something back and so part of our job as
Educators is to help students use these
tools in a way that will ensure their
long-term success with these tools right
so I'm not saying that they can't just
do whatever they want and make some of
their first assignments work I think
they could I think they could be like
unprincipled with the prompts and just
throw it in there and get code and you
know submit that code but we're going
for longer term Effectiveness here right
we have students who may not take
another CS course we need to keep them
in mind we have students who are going
to want to eventually be software
Engineers Security Experts phds in
computer science right so we have a
number of audiences that we're talking
about and we think they all need to know
the fundamental skills of programming
still even though you know they have
this power tool at their expense now
speaking of the fundamental skills for
programming because of my my Hardware
background I'm this huge fan of teaching
mental models in classes like what is
the mental model of computation like how
do you imagine the computer is executing
as you write the code and ideally a
professional computer scientists should
be able to take okay well this is kind
of the my interpretation this is my
mental model for when I'm working in
Python if I really want to drill this
down I can turn that into assembly and
if I really had to into a machine and
even think about how this is working
within the cache subsystems and virtual
memory and all these things I want them
to be able to play those things out
we are changing the first class and I
think the first class is going to be
doing some things much better than
before like teaching problem
decomposition and things like that I'll
mention that in a second but we are
doing something that's better but we may
not be teaching that how is the computer
working as well and so you can't just
change one course and think the rest of
the curriculum is going to work and so I
think the entire curriculum is going to
need to adjust in a way of just adapting
to these llms
the second piece for things getting
potentially more challenging is
instructors we're in a good place right
now as instructors in terms of how we
assign and grade homework
so grading this probably isn't going to
be a shock is not one of our favorite
things to do as faculty I mean it's
actually really important it's Central
to us understanding how our students
have learned but it's generally not the
most favorite thing that we do and what
a lot of instructors have done myself
included is for much of the introductory
sequence we have created assignments
that can be entirely auto-graded so we
Define functions incredibly well like
write a really good description this is
exactly what it needs to do
and then students write that one piece
of code and whether we like it or not
that is exactly when co-pilot does very
well in these llms do really well and so
the LMS are going to solve those very
easily already so we have to fix our
assignments just like it's a given but
it means that we're probably going to
have to rethink How We Do assessment and
so we're probably going to be writing
assignments that are much more
open-ended and we're probably going to
be grading those putting more care and
time integrating those potentially by
hand but I think these are all good
things for the community and for the
field but you can imagine how it's going
to be a bit of a shift for faculty and
it may take some time to be adopted as a
result and so if you're shifting to
homework that is more Broad in scope has
more code needs more human eyes on it
how does that scale within the Educators
side right you were talking about how
you've got things that could be
autograded before and then now you're
letting somebody generate this whole
project
how does that work from your end I think
there's a few things that are at Play We
At Large institutions like Dan and I are
at we have kind of armies of instructor
assistants instructional assistants that
help us and so we can engage them in
various tasks and so one of the roles
they heavily have now is helping
students in the labs solve these
auto-grade assignments and so you can
imagine they will still be in the labs
helping the students with these creative
assignments but now they're going to
have to have potentially a larger role
in assessing the success of those
there's been some really creative work
in assessment and so I'll mention a
couple of the ones I'm sure I'm gonna be
admitting some but one is students could
complete their project and then they
have to record a short video of them
explain the code that was in their
project and how it worked and you
actually assess them on that video and
their explanation of the code and how it
works right because those can be perhaps
shorter than trying to go through a
really big project and see how it works
there's a tool out of a UIUC called
prairielearn that helps with
these are still Auto graded but it helps
with the test setting where you can
write questions and have them created
kind of an in Sam or homework setting
the neat feature that is it can be
randomized and so you don't have to
worry as much about students kind of
leaking information to each other about
task content from quarter to quarter and
so because the randomization they have
to actually learn the skills and so you
can kind of engage them in these test
centers and so right now a big grading
burden on on faculty is exams and so you
can actually give more exams give more
frequent feedback to the students and
with without the same grading burden and
so that's the other kind of exciting
assessment piece in the different types
of Assessments like the example of the
video you gave I'm just thinking to
myself well the person could ask copilot
or chat GPT to give them a script right
and they can rehearse that when they
send you a video
I think this is a philosophical shift in
assessment that's kind of been gaining
momentum over the years and that's
that the assignments are all formative
and they should all be pretty low stakes
and the students should be doing them
for the process of learning and then and
it is unfair in some ways there's a
there's a lot of things right now where
you kind of grade them on were you
present at this time did you meet this
deadline at this time which are you
thinking about a diverse population of
students like you can imagine like a
working mother who's also trying to do
this grade them on were you here at this
time doesn't feel very Equitable to me
and so there's this whole movement for
grain for Equity that shifts much of the
assessment onto the exams and so yeah
the students could find multiple ways to
cheat on the homeworks but that's not
the point of the homework and the
homework's just to learn and it's a
small scale of grade but you still then
have those kind of controlled
environments where they're taking these
tests and that's where the grade
actually comes from it's going to take
some time to make that shift at least at
a number of schools my own included
assess that those take-home assignments
are a huge portion of grade and students
will love that because they can get all
this help and they can especially with
the auto graders that they don't write
their own test cases they just use the
auto readers the test cases right yeah
it was really depressing and they go to
the instructional staff the
instructional staff tends to give away
the answers that's actually a paper that
we published a few years ago and so the
students love this high stakes but tons
of help version of assessment but that
may not actually measure their their
level of knowledge and so it's going to
take a little bit of adjustment for
students and for faculty to do this
shift to where the exams are the bulk of
the grade also I'm I'm I'm not convinced
that cheating is going to be a problem
here it's very possible for example that
students cheat on our previous
assignments because the assignments were
not authentic you know in Industry no
one's going to come up to you and say
hey like from scratch you know write
this exact function takes two lists and
determines you know how many values are
equal between them it's like that's not
going to happen right you're going to be
doing something that has some sort of
business purpose and I kind of Wonder
and this this will play out one way or
another in the next few months but I
kind of wonder if we give students
authentic tasks now you're cheating
yourself right out of doing something of
value right like before you were
probably cheating yourself out of a
learning opportunity but you know how
can students know that right the
assignment's boring right it's like
write all these functions and then
something happens because of the magic
you know starter glue code we wrote so I
don't know I feel like if you give
students opportunities to learn what
they want to learn there's I don't know
I just don't think there's a reason to
cheat and also I mean I've been much
happier in my career recently when I
don't worry about it so it's like okay
I've got a bunch of students some of
them are going to cheat some of them are
not and I'm here to talk to the ones who
who want to learn so I don't know a lot
of people we're on some email lists for
example and a lot of people seem to be
panicking about it and I I kind of think
you know buddy you had a huge cheating
problem before I don't think it's going
to become worse now that you're giving
students authentic work to do right they
all want to be using you know
programming to do their jobs better or
make their lives better or the world
better they don't want to waste their
own time but if you give them a
decontextualized task it's like it's
super tempting to just cheat right
because what's the point right and so
I'm very hopeful I am not convinced that
cheating is gonna be a problem yeah
that's a good point and I think it's
very motivating for or
any student or anybody who's learning a
thing to be able to see a clear
connection to like an actual thing that
I made versus I'm writing functions to
pass these test cases is like not very
not very interesting intellectually so I
think if you structure the projects
where it's like oh I'm gonna actually
make this thing that does this thing
that seems pretty cool then yeah that's
definitely more motivating to actually
go through with it like yourself top my
head imagine if every student had to
make a landing page like a website who's
gonna cheat
like
like I want that and students are going
to want that too and so it's like well
okay like I may as well make it right
like this has a purpose so Leo you know
I'm curious you've been patiently
listening to that I'm curious what you
think about it oh I can't agree more I
think I mean we can leverage the
research right the Computing context is
kind of this well-established thing that
if you teach Computing in a context
that's meaningful to the students they
tend to learn more or engage more and
want to stay in the major more and I
think we're just going to be able to do
this right we for convenience sake and
because of the scale of the number of
students that we've had in our classes
we've kind of moved away from that and
gone to these auto-graded lots of
exciting assignments and I think this is
the impetus we need to go back to fun
creative interesting assignments that
the students are going to put time and
Care into because they want to not
because they have to so it sounds like
through our discussion you're really
excited about bringing large language
models into the classroom and kind of
what that means for you and your your
students and I wonder if there's
anything we didn't really touch on or
maybe something that was unexpected that
you think is going to make a really big
difference to you and your students I
think one of the things that we haven't
touched on yet that I'm I'm really
excited about is the piece of problem
decomposition and so over the years
because of this trend towards Auto
grading what's happened is all the
cognitive work of taking a big Computing
task and breaking it into smaller pieces
deciding what classes should exist what
function should exist all those
interfaces all that work that I think is
really interesting and exciting is now
done for students because the auto
grading structure just makes it so you
have to have these functions and they
just code the functions and so I think
that's really concerning just from a
software engineer in perspective that
students are learning how to program
without learning those core abilities as
software Engineers to take a large
problem break it down figure out what
the right interfaces are and that's a
lot of that's actually more art than
science I'd argue and so the more time
you have to practice it the better and I
am incredibly excited that llms are kind
of forcing our hand to make us step back
give larger programming tasks to them
and teach them the process of problem
decomposition explicitly you know in a
way that we've really never done before
I think that's a good place to wrap it
up on so if people want to hear more
about your upcoming book or maybe even
enroll in in your class Leo where can
they get some more information both Dan
and I have active LinkedIn pages and
we're happy to have folks follow us
there Manning publishing is the
publisher for our book and so we have
that book out on Early Access right now
it should be available entirely
electronically by August in time for the
start of the Fall quarter then it should
be out in print shortly thereafter cool
well this has been an interesting
discussion I mean large language models
are kind of that's the thing right now
everybody's trying to to stuff it into
every single product and I think getting
both of your perspective on where it
fits in and education has been very
interesting so thank you thank you very
much for coming on the show thank you
Jeremy for inviting us and for writing
such a great podcast we really
appreciate it thanks Jeremy this has
been Jeremy Jung for yourself for
engineering radio thanks for listening
thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se.radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through
our slack Channel at SC radio dot
slack.com you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of SC radio
is licensed under created Commons
license 2.5 thanks for listening
[Music]
thank you